<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../css/strict.xsl"?>
<PAGE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../css/schema.xsd">
<TITLE>Laurent Mazur&#xE9; - Curriculum Vitae</TITLE>
<PATH>perso/cve.xml</PATH>
<DATE><YEAR>2014</YEAR><MONTH>10</MONTH><DAY>19</DAY></DATE>
<CONTENT>
email: <X><T>lmazure.website@gmail.com</T><A>mailto:lmazure.website@gmail.com</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X><BR/>
homepage: <X><T>http://lmzr.perso.neuf.fr</T><A>http://lmzr.perso.neuf.fr</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X><BR/>
<X><T>French version</T><A>cvf.html</A><L>fr</L><F>HTML</F></X><BR/>
<BR/>

<B><U>Education:</U></B><BR/>
1987-1990: &#xC9;cole Centrale Paris, Applied Mathematics option<BR/>
<BR/>


<B><U>Experience:</U></B><BR/>

<B><X><T>Eurofins</T><A>http://www.eurofins.com</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X> &#x2014; Luxembourg, LU</B><BR/>
Eurofins Scientific, with 15 000 employees and 190 laboratories in 36 countries, is the world leader in food and biopharma product testing, and in the field of environmental laboratory services. It is also one of the global market leaders in agroscience, genomics, pharma discovery services and central laboratory services.<BR/>
<TEXTBLOCK>
  <BLIST><TITLE>Since December 2010: <U>EOL Development Manager</U></TITLE>
    <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>manager of the development team of Eurofins OnLine (EOL)</TITLE>
      <ITEM>EOL enables customers to place online orders of analyses, to track the progress of the work, and to access the results and conclusions of the measurements</ITEM>
      <ITEM>18 sites, each main Eurofins business having its own, managing more than 200,000 orders per year</ITEM>
      <ITEM>a cosmopolite team of two team leaders and 15-20 developers on several sites (Luxembourg, Nantes, Paris, Bangalore, Beijing)</ITEM>
    </BLIST></ITEM>
    <ITEM>team management: hiring, appraisals, administrative tasks, trainings&#x2026;</ITEM>
    <ITEM>project management: planning and task prioritisation, resource allocations, problem resolutions&#x2026;</ITEM>
    <ITEM>definition and tracking of the development processes</ITEM>
  </BLIST>
</TEXTBLOCK>
<SMALL>Functional domain: eCommerce, LIMS<BR/>
Technologies: Windows, C#, ASP.Net/MVC, HTML/CSS/JavaScript, jQuery, SQL Server, SSRS, SSIS/Talend, Red Hat JBoss Fuse<BR/>
Tools: Visual Studio, TFS, Subversion, Mantis, Cruise Control, NCover, FxCop, ReSharper, Selenium&#x2026;<BR/>
Processes/methodologies: mostly waterfall, some Scrum, some TDD<BR/></SMALL>
<BR/>

<B>KIKA Medical, now <X><T>Merge Healthcare</T><A>http://www.merge.com</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X> &#x2014; Nancy, FR</B><BR/>
KIKA Medical created some EDC solutions, then built and operated clinical trial Web sites based on them (around 10 new sites per year). Its latest platform, Veracity, a single page application, provided unmatched flexibility and advanced EDC capabilities including images and online adjudication. In financial distress, KIKA Medical was acquired in December 2010 by Merge Healthcare.<BR/>
<TEXTBLOCK>
  <BLIST><TITLE>July 2007 &#x2192; December 2010: <U>Software Development Manager</U></TITLE>
    <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>promoted functional manager of the development pole after the introduction of a matrix organization (the two other poles being product management and test)</TITLE>
      <ITEM>six developers and architects on three projects</ITEM>
      <ITEM>resource allocation to the projects, this point being rather delicate after some economic layoffs (July 2008)</ITEM>
      <ITEM>support of project managers: specification writing, management of sub-projects (Oracle performance, mitigation of IT issues&#x2026;)</ITEM>
    </BLIST></ITEM>
  </BLIST>
  <BLIST><TITLE>January 2006 &#x2192; July 2008: <U>Senior Project Manager</U><BR/>
    (I handled this position simultaneously to being Software Development Manager for one year)</TITLE>
    <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>management of the Veracity project</TITLE>
      <ITEM>8 R&amp;D persons helped by 7 off-shored testers and some other company employees who are temporarily involved in the project</ITEM>
      <ITEM>hands on participation in the project: specification, risk analysis, sanity testing, bug dispatch&#x2026;</ITEM>
    </BLIST></ITEM>
    <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>in an initial phase, this position involved a strong part of retrospective clean-up, the product was previously built in a total chaos for three years (the company failed to deliver a usable release for all this period; by implementing a real lifecycle, I was able to get such a release within 18 months):</TITLE>
      <ITEM>definition of the user needs</ITEM>
      <ITEM>cut of superfluous features, determination of the missing features</ITEM>
      <ITEM>specification and validation of the existing code</ITEM>
      <ITEM>specification, implementation and validation of the missing features</ITEM>
      <ITEM>respect of FDA regulations: risk analysis (FMEA), user needs → specification → design → validation traceability, training and user guides&#x2026;</ITEM>
    </BLIST></ITEM>
    <ITEM>participation to the definition and improvement of the Quality System Management which enabled KIKA Medical to get ISO9002 and ISO13485 certifications in October 2006</ITEM>
  </BLIST>
</TEXTBLOCK>
<SMALL>Functional domain: clinical trials, CDISC (ODM, CDASH, SDTM)<BR/>
Technologies: Red Hat Linux, Java EE/Swing, PHP, HTML/CSS/JavaScript, Apache/Tomcat, XML/XSL<BR/>
Tools: Eclipse, CVS/Subversion, Jira, Jasper Reports<BR/>
Processes/methodologies: waterfall<BR/></SMALL>
<BR/>

<B><X><T>General Electric Healthcare</T><A>http://www.gehealthcare.com</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X> &#x2014; Buc, FR</B><BR/>
General Electric Healthcare is a leader in medical technologies and services. GEHC provides medical imaging and information technologies, medical diagnostics, patient monitoring systems, drug discovery, biopharmaceutical manufacturing technologies and performance solutions services.<BR/>
<TEXTBLOCK>
  <BLIST><TITLE>January 2004 &#x2192; January 2006: <U>Six Sigma Master Black Belt</U></TITLE>
    <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>leading a project to merge four of the General Electric Healthcare review workstations: RA1000 (PACS station, Java/Windows, USA + India), RA600 (low tier, C++/Windows, Netherlands), Xeleris (nuclear medicine + PET, C++/Windows, Israel), and Advantage Workstation (high tier, C++/Linux, France + Hungary)</TITLE>
      <ITEM>these four products were created by teams from different parts of the company, each having their own priorities and their own ways to work</ITEM>
      <ITEM>the total revenues were larger than 900M$</ITEM>
    </BLIST></ITEM>
    <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>contribution to the writing of the software DFSS (Design For Six Sigma) training and teaching of this package to the Buc developers</TITLE>
      <ITEM>management of the quality initiatives in the department (100 persons) using Six Sigma methodology</ITEM>
      <ITEM>test automation</ITEM>
      <ITEM>automated verification of the document traceability</ITEM>
      <ITEM>implementation of defect metrics</ITEM>
      <ITEM>&#x2026;</ITEM>
    </BLIST></ITEM>
    <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>technical support to the projects</TITLE>
      <ITEM>choice of the technologies and prototyping for the features outside the usual AW domain</ITEM>
      <ITEM>port to 64 bits, support of Asian languages</ITEM>
      <ITEM>help to solve the trickiest technical problems (e.g. file system bug, performance issue&#x2026;)</ITEM>
      <ITEM>&#x2026;</ITEM>
    </BLIST></ITEM>
  </BLIST>
  <BLIST><TITLE>September 1997 &#x2192; January 2004: <U>Lead Software Designer</U></TITLE>
    <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>in charge of Advantage Workstation development</TITLE>
      <ITEM>2500 radiology review stations sold in 2003 (revenues = 130M$ for AW + 120M$ for the applications, 50% yearly increase, 40% of the market)</ITEM>
      <ITEM>team of 15-20 engineers (France + Hungary)</ITEM>
      <ITEM>various technologies: image processing, database (storing and accessing the images), client/server architecture, software bus, networking, printing, media (CD/DVD, magneto-optic disk)</ITEM>
    </BLIST></ITEM>
    <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>this position mainly consisted in</TITLE>
      <ITEM>the definition of the features with the marketing team and the writing of the detailed specification</ITEM>
      <ITEM>the workload estimation and the definition of the project timeline</ITEM>
      <ITEM>the risk analysis and mitigation</ITEM>
      <ITEM>with the whole team: conception, implementation, verification and validation</ITEM>
      <ITEM>the definition, application, and control of the development processes (some have been reused by other teams) in order to comply with the FDA rules and, above all, ensure a high quality level</ITEM>
      <ITEM>the management of the feedback from pilot sites</ITEM>
      <ITEM>the technical support of other teams writing applications installable on the AW station</ITEM>
    </BLIST></ITEM>
    <ITEM>nominated <B>Principal Engineer</B> in May 2001 (35 persons have been recognized for "technical excellence" among the 2000 R&amp;D engineers of GEHC)</ITEM>
  </BLIST>
  <BLIST><TITLE>April 1995 &#x2192; September 1997: <U>Software Engineer</U></TITLE>
    <ITEM>AW consolidation: library refactoring, intensive testing, and debugging; the code has become robust and could be safely used for the future releases</ITEM>
    <ITEM>improvement of the performance</ITEM>
    <ITEM>implementation of new features</ITEM>
    <ITEM>participation to some study councils to improve the quality and the productivity of software developments in GEHC</ITEM>
  </BLIST>
</TEXTBLOCK>
<SMALL>Functional domain: Radiology (DICOM, IHE, modalities - CT, MR, mammography, vascular&#x2026;-), FDA regulations (21 CFR Part 11, 510K&#x2026;), HIPAA<BR/>
Technologies: C++, X11/Motif. Python, Perl, Tcl/Tk, awk/sed, shells (sh, csh, ksh), Solaris/Linux, Informix/MySQL<BR/>
Tools: ClearCase, ClearDDTS, Purify, Valgrind, ProLint, CodeWizard<BR/>
Processes/methodologies: waterfall, Six Sigma/DFSS/DMAIC (Failure Mode and Effects Analysis - FMEA -, fishbone - Cause and Effect Diagram -, Quality Function Deployment, Critical to Quality - CTQ - flowdown&#x2026;), CMM, UML Design Patterns<BR/></SMALL>
<BR/>

<B><X><T>MENSI</T><A>http://mensi.free.fr/index_.htm</A><L>fr</L><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X>, now <X><T>Trimble</T><A>http://www.trimble.com/</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X> &#x2014; Neuilly-Plaisance, FR</B><BR/>
MENSI was a start-up having designed the first high-precision outdoor 3D scanners. Its products were used to scan oil or nuclear plants, buildings, prehistoric caves, sculptures… and building a CAD model of these. Despite its innovative technology, MENSI was a commercial failure. EDF, its main client, injected some money. MENSI was later bought by Trimble.<BR/>
<TEXTBLOCK>
  <BLIST><TITLE>September 1992 &#x2192; April 1995: <U>R&amp;D Engineer</U></TITLE>
    <ITEM>design and coding of 3DIpsos, a software processing data measured by a 3D scanner, this was one of the first products in this domain</ITEM>
    <ITEM>quality engineer</ITEM>
    <ITEM>system administrator (Unix)</ITEM>
  </BLIST>
</TEXTBLOCK>
<SMALL>Functional domain: 3D modelling of real world<BR/>
Technologies: C, OpenGL, Image Processing, Irix<BR/>
Tools: RCS<BR/></SMALL>
<BR/>

<B><X><T>EDF DER</T><A>http://retd.edf.fr</A><L>fr</L><F>HTML</F></X> &#x2014; Clamart, FR<BR/>
CADCentre, now <X><T>AVEVA</T><A>http://www.aveva.com</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X> &#x2014; Cambridge, GB</B><BR/>
CADCentre, later renamed AVEVA, designs and markets Plant Design Management System (PDMS), a Computer Aided Design software used to design oil, chemical or nuclear plants.<BR/>
<TEXTBLOCK>
  <BLIST><TITLE>May 1992 &#x2192; September 1992: <U>Debriefing of Civil National Service</U> (in EDF)</TITLE>
    <ITEM>participation to the specification of new PDMS features: links with a technical data management system, enhancements of the catalogue capabilities&#x2026;</ITEM>
  </BLIST>
  <BLIST><TITLE>February 1991 &#x2192; May 1992: <U>Civil National Service</U></TITLE>
    <ITEM>coding of some tools for test and configuration management: CADCentre was switching from Prime to Unix</ITEM>
    <ITEM>clean up and rationalization of PDMS code; the software, created in 1974, was becoming more and more difficult to maintain</ITEM>
    <ITEM>improvement of the scripting language of PDMS, expressions for database requests were much more powerful</ITEM>
  </BLIST>
  <BLIST><TITLE>June 1990 &#x2192; February 1991: <U>Preparation of Civil National Service</U> (in EDF)</TITLE>
    <ITEM>interface between PDMS and the Standard d&#x2019;&#xC9;change et de Transfert (SET)</ITEM>
    <ITEM>specification and prototyping of new features in PDMS: automated naming, management and application of coherency rules in the database&#x2026;</ITEM>
  </BLIST>
</TEXTBLOCK>
<SMALL>Functional domain: CAD, nuclear plants<BR/>
Technologies: Primos/Irix, Fortran, C, Lex/Yacc, GL/OpenGL<BR/></SMALL>
<BR/>

<B><U>Languages:</U></B><BR/>
French: mother tongue<BR/>
English: fluent<BR/>
<BR/>

</CONTENT>
</PAGE>