<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../css/strict.xsl"?>
<PAGE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../css/schema.xsd">
<TITLE>HTTPD methods</TITLE>
<PATH>notes/httpdmethods.xml</PATH>
<DATE><YEAR>2016</YEAR><MONTH>9</MONTH><DAY>12</DAY></DATE>
<CONTENT>

HTTP/1.1 methods
<TABLE>
<ROW><CELL>HEAD</CELL>
<CELL>Asks for the response identical to the one that would correspond to a GET request, but without the response body.</CELL></ROW>
<ROW><CELL>GET</CELL>
<CELL>
Requests a representation of the specified resource. Note that GET should not be used for operations that cause side-effects, such as using it for taking actions in web applications. One reason for this is that GET may be used arbitrarily by robots or crawlers, which should not need to consider the side effects that a request should cause. See safe methods below.<BR/>
The semantics of the GET method change to a "conditional GET" if the request message includes an <CODEROUTINE>If-Modified-Since</CODEROUTINE>, <CODEROUTINE>If-Unmodified-Since</CODEROUTINE>, <CODEROUTINE>If-Match</CODEROUTINE>, <CODEROUTINE>If-None-Match</CODEROUTINE>, or <CODEROUTINE>If-Range</CODEROUTINE> header field. A conditional GET method requests that the entity be transferred only under the circumstances described by the conditional header field(s) otherwise 304 is returned.<BR/>
The semantics of the GET method change to a "partial GET" if the request message includes a <CODEROUTINE>Range</CODEROUTINE> header field. A partial GET requests that only part of the entity be transferred.
</CELL></ROW>
<ROW><CELL>POST</CELL>
<CELL>
Submits data to be processed (e.g., from an HTML form) to the identified resource. The data is included in the body of the request. This may result in the creation of a new resource or the updates of existing resources or both.</CELL></ROW>
<ROW><CELL>PUT</CELL>
<CELL>
Uploads a representation of the specified resource.</CELL></ROW>
<ROW><CELL>DELETE</CELL>
<CELL>
Deletes the specified resource.</CELL></ROW>
<ROW><CELL>TRACE</CELL>
<CELL>
Echoes back the received request, so that a client can see what intermediate servers are adding or changing in the request.</CELL></ROW>
<ROW><CELL>OPTIONS</CELL>
<CELL>
Returns the HTTP methods that the server supports for specified URL. This can be used to check the functionality of a web server by requesting '*' instead of a specific resource.</CELL></ROW>
<ROW><CELL>CONNECT</CELL>
<CELL>
Converts the request connection to a transparent TCP/IP tunnel, usually to facilitate SSL-encrypted communication (HTTPS) through an unencrypted HTTP proxy.</CELL></ROW>
<ROW><CELL>PATCH</CELL>
<CELL>
Is used to apply partial modifications to a resource.</CELL></ROW>
</TABLE>
<BR/>

HTTP/1.0 is defined by <X><T>RFC1945</T><A>javascript:do_reference("rfc/1945")</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X>.<BR/>
HTTP/1.1 is defined by <X><T>RFC2616</T><A>javascript:do_reference("rfc/2616")</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X>.<BR/>
The PATCH method is defined by <X><T>RFC5789</T><A>javascript:do_reference("rfc/5789")</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X>.

</CONTENT>
</PAGE>



