<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../css/strict.xsl"?>
<PAGE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../css/schema.xsd" xml:lang="en">
<TITLE>JavaScript</TITLE>
<PATH>notes/javascript.xml</PATH>
<DATE><YEAR>2021</YEAR><MONTH>2</MONTH><DAY>21</DAY></DATE>
<CONTENT>
<BLIST><TITLE><U><B>Types</B></U></TITLE>
  <ITEM>Number: Double precision 64-bit floating point values. It can be used to represent both, integers and fractions.</ITEM>
  <ITEM>String: Represents a sequence of Unicode characters</ITEM>
  <ITEM>Boolean: Represents logical values, true and false</ITEM>
  <ITEM>Null: Represents an intentional absence of an object value</ITEM>
  <ITEM>Undefined: Denotes value given to all uninitialized variables</ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE><U><B>Boolean</B></U></TITLE>
  <ITEM>All the following lines of code create Boolean objects with an initial value of false:
  <CODESAMPLE>var myBoolean=new Boolean();<BR/>
  var myBoolean=new Boolean(0); <BR/>
  var myBoolean=new Boolean(null); <BR/>
  var myBoolean=new Boolean("");<BR/>
  var myBoolean=new Boolean(false); <BR/>
  var myBoolean=new Boolean(NaN);</CODESAMPLE>
  And all the following lines of code create Boolean objects with an initial value of true:
  <CODESAMPLE>var myBoolean=new Boolean(true); <BR/>
  var myBoolean=new Boolean("true");<BR/>
  var myBoolean=new Boolean("false");<BR/>
  var myBoolean=new Boolean("Richard");</CODESAMPLE></ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE><U><B>Arrays</B></U></TITLE>
  <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE>Array Creation</TITLE>
    <ITEM>regular array (add an optional integer argument to control array’s size)
    <CODESAMPLE>var myCars=new Array();<BR/>
    myCars[0]="Saab";<BR/>
    myCars[1]="Volvo";<BR/>
    myCars[2]="BMW";</CODESAMPLE></ITEM>
    <ITEM>condensed array
    <CODESAMPLE>var myCars=new Array("Saab","Volvo","BMW");</CODESAMPLE></ITEM>
    <ITEM>literal array
    <CODESAMPLE>var myCars=["Saab","Volvo","BMW"];</CODESAMPLE></ITEM>
  </BLIST></ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE><U><B>Objects</B></U></TITLE>
  <ITEM>The <CODEROUTINE>delete</CODEROUTINE> operator removes a property from an object.</ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE><U><B>Regular Expressions</B></U></TITLE>
  <ITEM>Syntax<BR/>
  <CODESAMPLE>var txt=new RegExp(pattern,modifiers);</CODESAMPLE>
  or
  <CODESAMPLE>var txt=/pattern/modifiers;</CODESAMPLE></ITEM>
  <ITEM>Modifiers<BR/>
  <CODEROUTINE>i</CODEROUTINE> - case-insensitive matching<BR/>
  <CODEROUTINE>g</CODEROUTINE> - global match (find all matches rather than stopping after the first match)<BR/>
  <CODEROUTINE>m</CODEROUTINE> - multiline matching<BR/>
  </ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE><U><B>Popup Boxes</B></U></TITLE>
  <ITEM>Alert Box<BR/>
  An alert box is often used if you want to make sure information comes through to the user.<BR/>
  When an alert box pops up, the user will have to click "OK" to proceed.
  <CODESAMPLE>alert("sometext");</CODESAMPLE></ITEM>
  <ITEM>Confirm Box<BR/>
  A confirm box is often used if you want the user to verify or accept something. <BR/>
  When a confirm box pops up, the user will have to click either "OK" or "Cancel" to proceed. <BR/>
  If the user clicks "OK", the box returns true. If the user clicks "Cancel", the box returns false.
  <CODESAMPLE>confirm("sometext");</CODESAMPLE></ITEM>
  <ITEM>Prompt Box<BR/>
  A prompt box is often used if you want the user to input a value before entering a page.<BR/>
  When a prompt box pops up, the user will have to click either "OK" or "Cancel" to proceed after entering an input value.<BR/>
  If the user clicks "OK" the box returns the input value. If the user clicks "Cancel" the box returns null.
  <CODESAMPLE>prompt("sometext","defaultvalue");</CODESAMPLE></ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE><U><B>Events</B></U></TITLE>
  <ITEM><BLIST><TITLE><CODEROUTINE>MouseEvent</CODEROUTINE></TITLE>
    <ITEM><CODEROUTINE>pageX</CODEROUTINE> / <CODEROUTINE>pageY</CODEROUTINE>: Relative to the top left of the fully rendered content area in the browser. This point could be anywhere in the browser window and can actually change location if there are embedded scrollable pages embedded within pages and the user moves a scrollbar.</ITEM>
    <ITEM><CODEROUTINE>screenX</CODEROUTINE> / <CODEROUTINE>screenY</CODEROUTINE>: Relative to the top left of the physical screen, this reference point only moves if you increase or decrease the number of monitors or the monitor resolution.</ITEM>
    <ITEM><CODEROUTINE>clientX</CODEROUTINE> / <CODEROUTINE>clientY</CODEROUTINE>: Relative to the upper left edge of the content area (the viewport) of the browser window. This point does not move even if the user moves a scrollbar from within the browser.</ITEM>
  </BLIST></ITEM>
</BLIST>
<U><B>Template literals (a.k.a. template strings)</B></U>
<CODESAMPLE>console.log(`Current value is ${value}`)</CODESAMPLE><BR/>
<BR/>
<U><B>nullish coalescing operator (<CODEROUTINE>??</CODEROUTINE>)</B></U><BR/>
The nullish coalescing operator (<CODEROUTINE>??</CODEROUTINE>) is a logical operator that returns its right-hand side operand when its left-hand side operand is null or undefined, and otherwise returns its left-hand side operand.<BR/>
This can be contrasted with the logical OR (<CODEROUTINE>||</CODEROUTINE>) operator, which returns the right-hand side operand if the left operand is any falsy value, not only null or undefined. In other words, if you use <CODEROUTINE>||</CODEROUTINE> to provide some default value to another variable foo, you may encounter unexpected behaviors if you consider some falsy values as usable (e.g., <CODEROUTINE>''</CODEROUTINE> or <CODEROUTINE>0</CODEROUTINE>).<BR/>
<BR/>
<U><B>optional chaining operator (<CODEROUTINE>?.</CODEROUTINE>)</B></U><BR/>
The optional chaining operator (<CODEROUTINE>?.</CODEROUTINE>) functions similarly to the <CODEROUTINE>.</CODEROUTINE> chaining operator, except that instead of causing an error if a reference is nullish (null or undefined), the expression short-circuits with a return value of undefined. When used with function calls, it returns undefined if the given function does not exist.<BR/>
<CODESAMPLE>myVar.myFunc?.()<BR/>
myVar.myArray?.[0]</CODESAMPLE>
<BR/>
<U><B>Styling console output</B></U><BR/>
You can use the <CODEROUTINE>%c</CODEROUTINE> directive to apply a CSS style to console output:<BR/>
<CODESAMPLE>console.log("This is %cMy stylish message", "color: yellow; font-style: italic; background-color: blue;padding: 2px");</CODESAMPLE>
<BR/>
<U><B>Declaring properties with a variable of the same name</B></U><BR/>
<CODESAMPLE>const firstName = "John";<BR/>
const lastName = "Doe";<BR/>
const person = {<BR/>
<TAB/>firstName: firstName,<BR/>
<TAB/>lastName: lastName<BR/>
};</CODESAMPLE>
can be written<BR/>
<CODESAMPLE>const person = {<BR/>
<TAB/>firstName,<BR/>
<TAB/>lastName<BR/>
};</CODESAMPLE>
<BR/>
<U><B><CODEROUTINE>script</CODEROUTINE>’s <CODEROUTINE>defer</CODEROUTINE> and <CODEROUTINE>async</CODEROUTINE></B></U><BR/>
<CODESAMPLE>&lt;script src="sample.js" defer&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</CODESAMPLE>
<BLIST>
  <ITEM>If <CODEROUTINE>async</CODEROUTINE> is present: The script is executed asynchronously with the rest of the page (the script will be executed while the page continues the parsing)</ITEM>
  <ITEM>If <CODEROUTINE>async</CODEROUTINE> is not present and <CODEROUTINE>defer</CODEROUTINE> is present: The script is executed when the page has finished parsing</ITEM>
  <ITEM>If neither <CODEROUTINE>async</CODEROUTINE> or <CODEROUTINE>defer</CODEROUTINE> is present: The script is fetched and executed immediately, before the browser continues parsing the page</ITEM>
</BLIST>
</CONTENT>
<X><T>links</T><A>../links/javascript.html</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X>
</PAGE>