<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../css/strict.xsl"?>
<PAGE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../css/schema.xsd" xml:lang="en">
<TITLE>MedDRA</TITLE>
<PATH>notes/meddra.xml</PATH>
<DATE><YEAR>2010</YEAR><MONTH>10</MONTH><DAY>25</DAY></DATE>
<CONTENT>
<BLIST><TITLE>MedDRA is a terminology for coding all medical information obtained during all phases of development and marketing:</TITLE>
<ITEM>Symptoms</ITEM>
<ITEM>Signs</ITEM>
<ITEM>Diseases</ITEM>
<ITEM>Diagnoses</ITEM>
<ITEM>Indications</ITEM>
<ITEM>Investigations/Procedures</ITEM>
<ITEM>Medical/Social History</ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE>Excluded from MedDRA</TITLE>
<ITEM>term qualifiers - Frequent, rare, mild, severe (there are exceptions)</ITEM>
<ITEM>numerical values - Potassium value of 3.0 mg/dL</ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE>MedDRA is organized with the following hierarchy (numbers are for MEdDRA 8.1):</TITLE>
<ITEM>System Organ Class (SOC) 26</ITEM>
<ITEM>High-Level Group Terms (HLGT) 332</ITEM>
<ITEM>High-Level Terms (HLT) 1683</ITEM>
<ITEM>Preferred Terms (PT) - A PT represents a single unique medical concept 16976</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lower-Level Terms (LLT) - <BLIST><TITLE>A LLT has one of the following relationships to the Preferred Term (PT)</TITLE>
<ITEM>Synonym</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lexical variant</ITEM>
<ITEM>Quasi-synonym</ITEM></BLIST>
62950</ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE>The 26 SOC:</TITLE>
<ITEM>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cardiac disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Congenital, familial and genetic disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ear and labyrinth disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Endocrine disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Eye disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gastrointestinal disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>General disorders and administration site conditions</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hepatobiliary disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Infections and infestations</ITEM>
<ITEM>Immune system disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Injury, poisoning and procedural complications</ITEM>
<ITEM>Investigations</ITEM>
<ITEM>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified (including cysts and polyps)</ITEM>
<ITEM>Nervous system disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pregnancy, puerperium and perinatal conditions</ITEM>
<ITEM>Psychiatric disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Renal and urinary disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Reproductive system and breast disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Social circumstances</ITEM>
<ITEM>Surgical and medical procedures</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vascular disorders</ITEM>
</BLIST>
The dictionary allows multiaxial coding: certains PT terms can be found in more than one SOC. But, in each SOC, each PT is represented by only one HLT and one HLGT. Each PT has a primary pathway that must be used for the initial analysis.<BR/>
<BLIST><TITLE>LLT may be a non-current term</TITLE>
<ITEM>Ambiguous, vague, misspelled, outdated terms</ITEM>
<ITEM>Terms derived from other terminologies that do not comply with MedDRA rules</ITEM>
<ITEM>Flagged as non-current</ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE>MedDRA also supports Special Search Categories (SSC) that contain clinical concepts relative to a similar etiology that cross SOCs. They generally group PTs relevant to a disease or a syndrome. In MedDRA 7.0:</TITLE>
<ITEM>Bone Marrow Depression</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cardiac Ischaemia</ITEM>
<ITEM>Haemorrhage</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hypersensitivity Reactions</ITEM>
<ITEM>Immediate Hypersensitivity and AnaphlyacticReactions</ITEM>
<ITEM>Oedema</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pain</ITEM>
<ITEM>Premalignant Lesions</ITEM>
<ITEM>Secondary Immunocompromised State</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thrombosis</ITEM>
<ITEM>Upper GI Bleeding/Perforation</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vasculitis</ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE>MaeDRA aslo contains Standardized MedDRA Queries (SMQs). They will eventually replace SSCs. The result for a COOPERATIVE effort between CIOMS and ICH (MSSO). They are groupings of MedDRA terms, ordinarily at the Preferred Term (PT) level, that relate to a defined medical condition or area of interest. Terms included in a given SMQ may relate to relevant signs, symptoms, diagnoses, syndromes, physical findings, laboratory and other physiologic test data… In Production (as of 2005-10-11)</TITLE>
<ITEM>Acute Renal Failure</ITEM>
<ITEM>HaemolyticDisorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hepatic Disorders</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rhabdomyolysis/Myopathy</ITEM>
<ITEM>Severe Cutaneous Adverse Reactions</ITEM>
<ITEM>Torsades de Pointes/QT Prolongation</ITEM>
</BLIST>
<BLIST><TITLE>Some details</TITLE>
<ITEM>British English spelling is used at the PT level and above. American spellings are included at the LLT level<BR/>
Capitalization is used for the first letter of each term, proper names, and abbreviations</ITEM>
<ITEM>Universally accepted abbreviations can be found at the LLT</ITEM>
<ITEM>Natural word order is maintained at the PT level except when reversal of words allows similar terms to be grouped together</ITEM>
<ITEM>Punctuation is limited to apostrophes in people's names and hyphens in some terms</ITEM>
<ITEM>NEC = Not Elsewhere Classified (When terminology does not allow for specificity of reported verbatim)</ITEM>
<ITEM>NOS = Not Otherwise Specified (When reported verbatim is not specific) Eliminated from PTs in 2003 in Version 6.1 (The NOS PTs were demoted to LLTs, and the equivalent non-NOS LLTs were promoted to PTs: 4,236 changes!)</ITEM>
<ITEM>Numeric codes are 8 digits, starting with first code of 10000001.<BR/>
Initially assigned alphabetically by term. New terms are assigned sequentially<BR/>
Codes are never reused<BR/>
"Codes" are not really coded information, do not reflect organization of dictionary: codes are just identification numbers</ITEM>
</BLIST>
The dictionary is updated twice a year. Major updates are indicated by an increment of the first digit, minor ones by an increment of the second.<BR/>
<BR/>
If a patient experiences a recurring given AE, this one is counted only once with a severity equal to the greatest severity of all occurrences.
</CONTENT>
</PAGE>