<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../css/strict.xsl"?>
<PAGE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../css/schema.xsd">
<TITLE>8D (Eight Disciplines) Problem Solving Process</TITLE>
<PATH>quality/8D.xml</PATH>
<DATE><YEAR>2021</YEAR><MONTH>1</MONTH><DAY>11</DAY></DATE>
<CONTENT>
<NLIST>
<ITEM><B>Use Team Approach</B><BR/>
Establish a small group of people with the knowledge, time, authority and skill to solve the problem and implement corrective actions. The group must select a team leader.
</ITEM>
<ITEM><B>Describe the Problem</B><BR/>
Describe the problem in measurable terms. Specify the internal or external customer problem by describing it in specific terms.
</ITEM>
<ITEM><B>Implement and Verify Short-Term Corrective Actions</B><BR/>
Define and implement those intermediate actions that will protect the customer from the problem until permanent corrective action is implemented. Verify with data the effectiveness of these actions.
</ITEM>
<ITEM><B>Define end Verify Root Causes</B><BR/>
Identify all potential causes which could explain why the problem occurred. Test each potential cause against the problem description and data. Identify alternative corrective actions to eliminate root cause.
</ITEM>
<ITEM><B>Verify Corrective Actions</B><BR/>
Confirm that the selected corrective actions will resolve the problem for the customer and will not cause undesirable side effects. Define other actions, if necessary, based on potential severity of problem.
</ITEM>
<ITEM><B>Implement Permanent Corrective Actions</B><BR/>
Define and implement the permanent corrective actions needed. Choose on-going controls to insure the root cause is eliminated. Once in production, monitor the long-term effects and implement additional controls as necessary.
</ITEM>
<ITEM><B>Prevent Recurrence</B><BR/>
Modify specifications, update training, review work flow, improve practices and procedures to prevent recurrence of this and all similar problems.
</ITEM>
<ITEM><B>Congratulate Your Team</B><BR/>
Recognize the collective efforts of your team. Publicize your achievement. Share your knowledge and learning.
</ITEM>
</NLIST>
<LINE/>
<BLIST><TITLE>Links</TITLE>
  <ITEM><X><T>Management for the Rest of Us</T><A>https://mftrou.com/8d-problem-solving/</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X></ITEM>
  <ITEM><X><T>Wikipedia</T><A>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eight_disciplines_problem_solving</A><L>en</L><F>HTML</F></X></ITEM>
</BLIST>
</CONTENT>
</PAGE>